hello everyone and welcome to the cloud
migration for beginners my name is
Nicola and I'm a software developer and
one of the areas that I'm working on is
cloud migration toing together with me I
have Ricardo yeah thank you I am Ricardo
indeed a software engineer from the
Contra plane team in business Central uh
our team also deals besides Cloud
migration also with the environment
Administration
features so we have prepared a lot of
content for you that we will try to fit
within approximately 1 hour time frame
we are going to start with the
introduction where we are going to show
to you all of the important Concepts
around the cloud migration and you will
be able to see how does the cloud
migration looks end to endend and then
for the next part we are going to go
through the steps that are necessary to
be done for the cloud migration so we
will show you how you can prepare for
the cloud migration how to set it up and
replicate the data important things
around the data upgrade and how do you
complete the cloud migration go live and
we are going to end with troubleshooting
section one important thing that I would
like to say before we begin is that some
functionality we are going to explore in
depth however some functionality we are
going to only mention with a reference
to the documentation so you can read it
on your own and this is because it would
not fit the time
frame so for the introduction we are
going to start with the why should you
use the cloud migration tooling I'm
going to show you some endtoend flow how
does it look like and we are going to
end up discussing which possible Cloud
migration paths are
available for why you should use the
cloud migration tooling there are two
main reasons and they are that it is the
fastest and safest way to migrate the on
Prem data into sauce the reason why it
is the fastest way is because it is
using SQL to SQL copy so it is going to
take one SQL database and by using
technology which is named Azure data
Factory it is going to use it to move
the data from the on Prem database into
the SAS database if we compare this to
some other tooling like rapid start or
any other Al based solution SQL to SQL
copy is much
faster the second reason why we would
recommend you to use the cloud migration
tool link is because it is the safest
way to run the cloud
migration we have streamlined the
process it has been used by the
thousands of Partners unfortunately I
cannot tell you how many migrations
exactly we had but it is counted in tens
of thousands of unique Cloud migrations
for these reasons we have invested a lot
in preventing you from making mistakes
because discovering mistakes after
goingo life can be quite costly to fix
so the tooling is built to highlight all
of the mistakes that you can do and to
prevent you from actually making them
and not realizing that you have done the
mistake we have also looked into which
data should be replicated and which
should be left on Prem for all of the
Microsoft on tables so you're going to
be moving only the data that is
necessary to the cloud and at the end
the tooling is capable to detect data
issues in some cases it can autocorrect
them and in case that it cannot out
correct the issues it's going to
highlight them either as errors or as
warnings as I have said we have a large
community of partners that is using it
which is also able to help you with some
tips and tricks around the tooling so I
would recommend to you to check out the
documentation because we have listed a
lot of information here also after you
have read it for the first time I would
recommend to come from time to time and
to check for updates because we are
constantly updating the documentation
with useful
information one of the things I would
really like to ask you to do is to join
us on ymer as you can see we have a
large community here almost 1,200
partners that are active on this channel
so if you have any problems you can ask
the question here you can reach out to
us with the feedback or any questions
that you have and it's also an excellent
way to interact with the other partners
that are doing the Cloud migration and
to share the experiences
so this was all for why should you use
the cloud migration tool that we have
shipped and now I'm going to show you
how does the process look like end to
end so here I have a recording ready
because this process would take
approximately 40 minutes and we are
going to speed it up so you will be able
to see how does it look
like to access the cloud migration toink
you simply search for it on the cloud
migration management and when you go to
this page here you will see that we have
raised the notification that can take
you to the setup
wizard on this step only thing that you
need to do is to choose the product from
which you are migrating for this demo we
are going to choose the earlier version
of the business Central because we want
to migrate the database that is coming
from 14 on the next step I need to
provide the SQL connection string in the
tool tip you can see how it is looking
like so you can Define it in an easy way
I'm going to quickly copy paste it for
this demo because I have it
ready so when I enter the SQL connection
string here when I invoke the next
action
here then we are going to create the
Azure data Factory Pipeline and we will
give you the access key for
it because we are using on Prem SQL
Server here you will need to configure
it if you were using Azure SQL database
it would not be necessary Ricardo is
going to talk about it a bit
more so here we are waiting for it and
on this step we are going to give you
the instructions on how you can set up
the integration runtime on your box to
expose the on Prem database to the Azure
data Factory the first step that you
would need to do is to download and
install the integration runtime because
we're are using the on Prem SQL and then
when it installs you can copy paste the
authentication key there will be a small
window where you can provide it and that
is going to connect it to the Azure data
Factory for the time reasons I have
already done this and I have
pre-installed integration runtime which
also allows me to show you one cool
thing many partners are actually
reinstalling the integration runtime if
they want to change the key that is not
necessary because you can use Powershell
to change the runtime to change the
connection that the integration runtime
is using so to do this you simply Define
the r key like variable like here and
then you can use a Powershell script
that is coming with the integration
runtime it's called like register
integration runtime and you provide the
Gateway key that you have just defined
above and if you run it like this then
it is going to reconfigure the
integration runtime that is already
installed to connect to the different
Azure data Factory pipeline so this is
going to save you significant amount of
time if you're running multiple Cloud
migrations so if you run this poell
script you can see that the integration
runtime is connecting to the service now
it has connected so if I go back to the
client and if I invoke next now the
integration runtime is going to try to
read the on Prem database and if we
rewind the video a little bit because
this takes like 10 to 15
seconds and here you can see it's
successfully connected we see the on
Prem companies we we going to select all
of them and now we can finish the
wizard the migration has been set up it
can take you directly to the UI so you
can manage the cloud migration like here
and the status that you can see here is
that it is creating companies so we are
going to automatically create all of the
companies that you have selected on The
Wizard and this step we recommend that
you do immediately after your provision
the tenant because it can save you time
when you decide to do the go live
migration there is no need to wait for
the creation of the companies which can
take few hours if you're moving 20 or 30
companies if you go for the companies
page here you will see that the
companies are created and the status is
changed ready for application and now we
can start moving the data to Sauce So
when you say that you want to start the
data replication now the replication
process is going to
start and you can track it on this page
by invoking refresh status section that
is here so if we invoke this refresh
status section A few time after like 5
to 10 minutes is going to connect and
you can see that we have
1,662 tables to copy so if we rewind the
video a little bit this number is going
to start going down and you can see that
the number of table successful is going
to start
increasing so if we are rewinding it
and here the thing that you can see is
that we have successfully copied all of
the tables the number is a little less
than 1,600 and that's because we don't
report the tables that had no date with
in them then if I tried to complete the
cloud migration go
life the thing that I'm going to get is
that I cannot do it because I did not
run the upgrad and I'm migrating from 14
and to fix that I can invoke the Run
data upgrade action and we are going to
warn you that you need to do this as a
last step we're going to be talking
about it a bit more later then if you
invoke the upgrade like
this the thing that is going to happen
is that you're going to lose the access
to the
environment because we will move the
tenant into the maintenance mode and the
only session that is going to be running
on the tenant is is the upgrate session
and this is great because you're not
going to get any data locks there will
not be any
instabilities and the last thing that I
would like to say you are also getting
an automatic roll back in case the
upgrade fails so you can patch the date
while it is running you can track the
status in the business Central admin
Center you can see that the data upgrade
is running here and in case it fails
you'll also get an error here together
with the stri
so if we run it a little bit
more as you can see here the upgrade has
succeeded so if we go back to the tenant
and if we refresh this window here we
are going to get the access
back so the tenant is
loading and if we go to the cloud
migration management page you can see
that the upgrade has completed
successfully so now we are able to
invoke complete the cloud migration and
do the actions that we need to do before
going
live so if I invoke this section then
the cloud migration is going to stop we
will deprovision all of the pipelines
and we will Market as
completed so as you have seen we have
moved three companies in approximately
12 minutes so this is how long it took
to copy so the tooling itself is
actually quite
quick okay so that was all for the demo
of the endtoend cloud migration and the
last topic for the introduction is what
are possible migration parts that you
can use for the cloud
migration so if you're planning to do
the s cloud migration and the customer
is on version that is before 14 the
first step is to upgrade to
14 14 is the lowest version that we
support for Direct on Prem upgrade or
for the direct Cloud
migration from 14 and also from all of
the versions that are before 23 you can
do a single step upgrade to the latest
version and then from the latest version
you can simply replicate to sauce or
from all of these versions that are from
14 to 22 you can do a direct Cloud
migration and then run the missing
upgrade in sauce to put it in words you
need to upgrade to version 14 and then
you can either replicate directly to sus
and run the upgradeing sus or you can
run the on Prem upgrade to the latest
version and then replicate data to Sauce
we are often getting questions which
option is better option one is much
simpler because you simply connect the
SQL database as you have seen in the
demo you replicate the data and then we
will run the upgrade for you option two
is more complex for you because you need
to do more work but it's giving you more
control over the upgrade process because
you're running it on
Prem usually the partners are using on
Prem upgrade for large tenants because
it is going to give them more control
and optimizations over the upgrade
process while the smaller tenants are
simply copied to SAS and directly
updated we are going to write a
dedicated documentation topic around
moving the large tenants with tips and
tricks how you can optimize the speed
because we are getting a lot of
questions in this area and for the last
thing for the cloud migration upgrade
flows we have an important upgrade
strategy announcement and this is that
we are stopping the direct upgrade and
Cloud migration path from Dynamics
business Central 14 in approximately
year and a half from now so in April
2025 together with version 26 it will
not be possible to Cloud migrate or
directly upgrade from version 4 14 to
version
26 the reason why we are doing this is
because we need to remove obsolet fields
and tables we have not been cleaning up
objects in a very long time actually
from version 12 so the amount of data
that we need to clean up is quite large
and the second reason why we need to do
this is because of the delocalization
effort that we are doing we are trying
to move all of the localizations into
separate extensions and for this we will
need to move the tables up and down and
for both of these efforts if we delete
any SQL objects we cannot support a
direct Cloud migration or upgrate
pot to explain this one in a little bit
more details so when we start working on
version 26 we are going to start with
introducing the breaking SQL changes and
we will delete the upgrade methods that
were there so you will see all of the
changes that we did when we start
working on version 26 and when version
26 is is released then version 25 is
going to become a jump build this means
that from all of these versions before
25 you will need to upgrade to 25 then
from 25 you will be able to upgrade to
26 on Prem and replicate the data or you
will be able to replicate the data from
25 and run the upgrade insu directly
from version
25 we are planning to introduce these
jump versions or to delete the objects
every five versions so the next jump
version would be 30 so there will be a
necessary upgrade step every five
versions so this is the current plan
that we are bringing to you because we
would like you to be ready to plan and
to adjust if you have any feedback for
us please reach out and let us know how
is this change affecting
you all right so this was all regarding
the introduction and now we are going to
move into the preparation step when
you're preparing for the cloud migration
essentially you need to do two steps one
is to align the SQL table definitions
and the second one is to clean up the
date aligning the table definitions
seems very complex in reality it's quite
simple because you only need to take
care of two things the first thing that
you must do is that you need to align
the primary keys so the primary keys in
the source table and in the destination
table must match exactly the second
thing that you need to do is that you
need to make sure that the field name
and the field type is matching in the
source and in the
Target if there is a difference in the
name and type we are going to throw an
error it's possible to move the data
with different lengths so we can move
the shorter lengths into the longer
fields that is not going to be seen as a
breaking
change everything else is optional so if
we have customized Fields here we can
skip them if you have different table
names we can handle them through the
table mappings so you will be able to
map the tables in the UI and the engine
will be able to move
them also if you have customizations
that you would like to move out of the
main tables as many people on Prem have
into the table extensions the cloud
migration tooling is able to do this
through simple table mappings and we are
going to show you this how does this one
work in few
moments the tool is completely ignoring
everything else so IDs if they are
different the tool does not care about
them because these properties are stored
in the object metadata and we are going
to ignore any other
differences when you are aligning the
fields one of the things that you will
probably need to do is that you will
need to introduce threel prefixes or
suffixes to the field names and many
partners have already done
this
so main questions that we are getting
here is how can we introduce these
threel prefixes in an easiest
way essentially there are three options
that you can do you can align the
definitions in C because C is only
looking at IDs when you're doing the
renames so in case that you want to do
this you can can import a fob with
renames as a separate upgrade step and
force sync the changes and then Cil is
going to keep the data in this case if
the IDS stay the same option number two
is probably used by most of the partners
you can use SQL scripts to alter the
table definitions or you can also use
them to copy the data from the old
schema onto the new schema because as I
have said the cloud migration tooling is
simply just looking at the SQL
definitions it's not looking at any
other object properties and the last
option is if you're a large partner that
is running on Prem upgrade as well you
can use the data transfer objects so you
can move the data from the Old Fields
into the new Fields data transfer object
is essentially a SQL query so it's quite
fast in moving the
date so that was all for aligning the
SQL definitions so for the next topic is
cleaning up the
data one big ask that we have for you
and you can do this task even before
starting the cloud migration is to run
invoke NV sanitized field commandlet to
eliminate non-printing characters from
code
Fields many customers that have been
running on our product for decades they
have nonprinting characters in Code
Fields like new line characters and SQL
server is not able to support these
characters so if you Cloud migrate with
this it's possible inside also to
sanitize the data but I would strongly
recommend that you do this step even
before starting the cloud migration
because you can clean up their
production database and they will be
happy to get rid of this data corruption
that is coming from many many years ago
the second thing to check is as code
Fields can have non-printing characters
so can company names so make sure that
there are no special characters or
trailing spaces if you leave them then
you will see that the replication is
failing for these specific
companies second thing that you can use
for cleaning up the data are the date
compression And archiving reports that
we have in the product we have a page
which is called Data Administration page
and it has ID of
9,035 and here we have basically put all
of the reports that you can use for data
cleanup or data compression so it's good
so you get an overview which reports are
there most of these reports they exist
in all of the versions of BC and nav so
you can use them even in these
products however you need to navigate to
them because this data Administration
page may not be available so this task
you can also do before going live on the
production database to clean up the data
as much as possible and to shrink the
data set so the upgrade and the cloud
migration goes
smoother all right so that was all about
the introduction and preparation Ricardo
can you show us the setup yes so that
was great so far uh we want to give a
closer look now into what are the uh
building blocks of the cloud migration
infrastructure so basically Let's uh
jump into what's uh happening behind the
hood of cloud migration so just to give
a very high level introduction of course
when we talk about Cloud migration uh
there's the assumption that there's
always a source environment that would
be a business Central own param
installation where you have your own SQL
Server database and a destination uh
business Central online environment
that's uh basically uh with a aure SQL
database so let's figure out what's
happening in between when we run Cloud
migration so the main technology we rely
on is the Azure data Factory which is an
Azure cloudbased data integration uh
service that takes care of uh moving and
transforming the data across different
data sources and the main component uh
that aure data Factory relies on is
pipelines so-called
pipelines and what are these pipelines
they are basically just a chain grouping
of activities and each of them can
either take care of indeed moving
transforming or controlling the flow of
the
data next uh the next component is the
um integration runtime this makes up the
compute layer of the cloud migration
infrastructure and in this setup uh
where we have indeed an on premise
installation of uh uh our business
Central um we require to install a
self-hosted integration runtime which
means this will actually be installed
within the private Network where the SQL
Server database lives and on the aure
side we also have an Azure integration
runtime and both of these will take care
uh on one side to pull the data outside
of the business Central environment on
Prem and bring it into to the
cloud on another hand it is also
possible to perform Cloud migration from
already uh a database that is already in
the cloud for example an asure SQL
database and in such case uh there will
not be a self-hosted integration run
time but an asure integration run time
again so that the whole process will
take place fully in the cloud also worth
mentioning the self-hosted integration
on time is also allowing a secure way to
copy the data from a private within a
private Network into to the cloud
another important thing is that uh with
this setup uh when you're running Cloud
migration from on Prem database uh
there's no need of a NST installation uh
at this point all that is needed is only
the
database so let's move next uh let's
figure out what's happening specifically
when we are initiating the cloud
migration setup uh phase uh when we are
in this page in the product that Nicola
has just shown us before so the very
first thing is about registration uh
registration of the integration runtime
with the Azure data Factory uh in the
back end we actually use load balancing
mechanism so that uh we have a set of
aure data factories available and we
always try to find the best one that is
the most suitable for running your own
uh Cloud migration so when we find a
proper aure data Factory to link your
integration runtime with uh we reserve
one and then that will exchange an
authentication key that would be the one
that is indeed inserted in the migration
setup and at this point the H data
Factory and your integration run time
are
linked so next step is the creation of a
preparation pipeline that's what um we
will proceed with and this uh is
basically responsible or per of
Performing some checks both on the on
premise database and on the business
Central online database so weely on the
integration run times to perform these
checks where are these specifically so
we for example want to to check that the
connectivity to the database works
correctly uh we want to check that the
versions of the databases are also
compatible and the compatibility level
for example so when these checks succeed
uh we create a set of stored
procedures and these also we will take
care for example on one side on Prem to
retrieve the list of tables to be copied
and on SAS we want to for example
retrieve the list of installed
extensions Next Step uh we create a
replication Pipeline and we provide as
an input to this pipeline the
information that we just collected so
indeed the list of table tables that
have to be migrated and instructions for
how to migrate them so this information
is provided as a metadata for this
pipeline but we will not yet run this
pipeline at this point we just leave it
there uh sitting ready to be
run so at this point if all the checks
succeed and everything worked fine with
the preparation pipeline we Mark the
online environment as correctly set up
so we conclude the setup step and uh we
are ready to proceed to the next
phase so there's one important thing to
call out because since the stored
procedures will actually apply some
changes to the on Prem database uh we
highly recommend to try the cloud
migration for the first time on a backup
of the production
database so that was it for the
introduction of the setup of cloud
migration we move on to the next step uh
that can answer some common questions
and a further setup that needs to be
done before actually starting to
replicate our data so the very first
thing is um a common question that could
be what is the best choice between uh
migrating from an onr database or an
aure SQL database So based on some very
recent improvements that we have applied
throughout the last year we can safly
claim that the migrations from aure SQL
are a very stable and fast way to
replicate your data they overcome some
limitations uh that would be uh not very
straightforward to accomplish with the
on Prem setup for example replication of
SQL field SQL variant fields and also
because of uh memory and performance
optimizations they can also handle
replication of large images into single
Fields however uh of course Ager SQL
database is not a free service so it
comes with a downside of having of being
charged for this service as long as the
database is online and act
we do recommend because of the high
volume of data being transferred to
choose a service tier that can satisfy
um High compute and input output
requirements so next one important thing
to remember as well uh when we're
working with Cloud migration is that if
there's any available updates for the
environment in the admin Center we
strongly recommend to postpone them to a
later date so that they don't interfere
with the cloud migration that we're
working on because if that happens
actually that the environment gets
updated while Cloud migration is still
enabled we would forcefully stop Cloud
migration and then you would be forced
to start over again deleting the
environment and starting from
scratch another important recommendation
that we have uh hold although is
optional um is to set up application
insights Telemetry on your environment
this can also be achieved from the admin
Center and it is particularly important
because if you do set it up then you
have telemetry available for all the
flows that involve Cloud migration so we
will see towards the end of the
presentation some specific use cases
where Telemetry can actually be
useful yeah so now we look into uh the
next feature that is table mappings so
let's figure out what exactly table
mappings mean so essentially the aim of
table mapping is to move custom fields
to table extensions in SAS and this is
specifically because on Prem you're
allowed to customize uh base tables but
in in SAS we are not so we want to be
provide you the ability to migrate also
these extra fields to SAS the
replication engine will also take care
of splitting the data if needed across
multiple table
extensions and the only very important
requirement at this point is that the
field names and data types must match
always between on pram and SAS so to
give also a better visual representation
of how this works we have a scenario
where indeed in SAS we are ex we are um
customizing the customer table besides
having the Microsoft fields we also have
some additional Fields And while running
Cloud migration we actually figure out
that we would like to migrate some of
the fields while some other fields we're
not interested in them so we could leave
them on Prem without migrating them but
on SAS indeed we cannot customize the
base customer table so we can only have
the Microsoft Fields there so the goal
here is to indeed migrate the additional
Fields into table extensions that are
owned by PTS
and with regards to the Microsoft Fields
uh the mapping of these fields between
on Prem and sus uh happens automatically
thanks to the replicate data property
set to true and these will indeed take
care of replicating the fields just
because the field names and types
exactly
match so the migration table mapping
feature instead will be the one taking
care of copying the custom fields to the
Target tables uh again if the field
names and types match
it is important to call out however as
niola mentioned before that the fields
in uh the on Prime table will have to be
renamed so that they match exactly the
fields in SAS so since in SAS the fields
in the table extensions will have a
prefix this change must also be
reflected on
Prem so now it's time to demonstrate it
live and I will hand over back to
Nicolas so he can give a live
demonstration of this feature in the
product thank you Ricardo so if you
would like to use this feature it's also
accessible from the cloud migration
management page and it's called managed
custom tables so if you open it from
here you could Define the migration
table mappings in this UI here by just
inlining the table definition however we
have seen that this process was error
prone for many users that were trying to
use this functionality so instead I
would recommend to use a dedicated page
that we have introduced which is called
add table
mappings so if if you invoke it here
it's going to open so here on this page
the only thing that you need to provide
in the first part is the name and if you
would like to provide it in a way so it
is not error prone in SQL if you take
the entire table name like this using
the square brackets together and if you
copy paste it here you will see that it
is automatically going to parse the
values and it will autocomplete the
other two field fields which is is the
data per company and the EP ID also if
you do it like this you will see that it
is escaped in SQL so it is not
containing slash so the next thing that
I would need to do here is to select
that we are mapping to the table
extensions you can filter the list here
and the only thing that I need to do is
to select to which table extension I
want to move the date and in this case
it would be the
pt1 now I could do this three times one
by one inserting one line by one however
the UI is supporting multi select and as
you have seen in ricard's example we do
want to split it into three extensions
so I'm going to select all three
extensions and if I invoke okay is going
to automatically insert three mappings
so this is saving you a lot of
clicks then let's do a customer so if I
would go to a customer table I would
simply select a customer here and if I
go here and I do the add table
mappings and here on the customer I can
select it and if I invoke okay I got
three custom records as well so by doing
this simple definition in less than a
minute I'm able to split two main tables
into three table extensions without
writing any
code to show you one small thing here if
we take a actual database that is not
Cil database so CL tables databases they
do not have the extension ID but in Al
this extension is going to have a
extension ID behind it and if you copy
it with the square brackets and when you
tab you can see it is able to parse out
the app ID so it's just an example how
it is going to prevent mistakes during
the data
entry one functionality that you have
here is that you can export the
definitions it's going to give you a
Json file that you can import later so
you don't need to type in the definition
multiple
times um also you able to provide these
table mappings programmatically if you
subscribe to the on insert default table
mappings event from code unit 401 hybrid
Cloud management so if you're are a
large partner that have a customized isv
solution and you would like to
automatically split these table m
mappings you can do it by code as well
and then each time when we complete the
wizard we are going to update the table
mappings all right so that was all back
to you Ricardo yep so now let's talk
about some things that we want to call
out uh still related to the setup step
although we will not go into a lot of
details here because uh there will also
be the what's new in Cloud uh Cloud
migration session that will elaborate
more into details yeah so the first
thing is that we want to call out the
ability now to include selectively
include or exclude tables from the cloud
migration so the base rule here is that
um you are allowed to change the setting
for the tables that are not classified
as sensitive and in principle any table
that you can write a pte on based on uh
then you will be able to change the
setting for such table again we will uh
have this session where we'll look into
the more into more specific details
the other feature is uh the ability to
keep user permissions while the cloud
migration is set up because until now
the base uh the default Behavior was
that uh when whenever Cloud migration is
set up we remove user permissions from
any existing user and you are able now
to disable this this default behavior
and always keep the permissions so this
could be particularly useful for
scenarios where for example service to
service to service authentication is
needed um or for the uh unsupported
scenario so we don't really recommend
doing this uh but moving additional
companies after going
live then so everything we've seen so
far is also possible for delegated
admins so in principle it will always be
a licensed super user that is able to
perform the cloud migration setup and
all the actions that follow but if you
are a delegated admin logged into the
customers's environment for example you
can perform such actions but we will ask
you to get permission from a licensed
user so specifically when you log in you
will be prompted with this screenshot
where you will be provided a link that
the customer will have to go to uh to be
able to Grant consent for you as a
delegated admin to run Cloud migration
or alter alternatively we also have a
small demonstration of how this could
happen if you're logged into an
environment as a licensed user with
super permissions then it is as easy as
using paid search and going to the
delegated admin consent for cloud
migration here here you will be able to
Grant consent for a delegated admin we
log who has granted consent and
similarly we can also revoke the consent
and this is mainly uh needed for
security reasons because um if you want
to Grant consent to an admin at any
point you want to revoke this consent
you should be able to do that still from
this page but if that's the case then
the cloud migration that is currently uh
running will stop so we jump to the next
section now and we will talk about how
exactly is the data replicated so let's
again look into a more schematic way to
figure out what exactly happens when we
click on run data replication under the
cloud migration management
page so at this point we have this
visualization that shows again all the
parties involved we are using again aure
data Factory pipelines and as we uh told
told you about earlier at the end of the
setup phase we had a replication
pipeline that was ready to be run so
this is the moment when clicking on run
data replication we actually start start
running this replication pipeline so the
main thing to call out here is that
there is an Azure blob storage component
that uh is used for staging area uh and
actually let's assume for now that this
replication is occurring when there is
an on premise SQL Server database as a
source so the aure blob storage um
staging area allows us uh to compress
the data so that we have a lower volume
of data to be transferred to the cloud
and this actually brings some optim
ations uh with regards to the speed that
it
takes so the integration runtime on
premise uh will perform some checks on
the tables on premise because the goal
is to figure out the data structure of
the tables and based on this figure out
how to actually perform the copy of the
tables to to to the cloud uh so for the
large tables for such tables that we
identify as large meaning that the size
exceeds 250 mbytes or there's more than
100,000 rows we will perform table copy
one by one exactly copying the table
from the source to the destination for
all the other tables that don't classify
as large we will perform Bal copy and
what does this mean we will actually uh
gather all these tables together we will
compress them we will chunk the records
serialize everything into a huge Json
and perform uh and actually copy all the
content into a single table uh adoc
table that is used for this purpose and
then migrate only this table to the
cloud and then the integration runtime
in the cloud will take care of
Performing the exact opposite so
decompressing distalizing and feeling
the records in the original
tables so the very first replication run
uh will take everything that is
currently on the on premise database and
migrate it fully to the cloud but this
doesn't mean that you're uh you cannot
perform any more replications because
you can still add or edit data on
premise and we rely on SQL change
tracking mechanism to keep track of the
changes and then perform additional
replication runs only on the Deltas so
this allows you to perform incremental
changes and migrate only what's new
every time to the
cloud now everything that we've saw here
is exactly possible uh also if you have
an nature SQL database as a source but
it's important to call out a very uh big
Improvement that we've made throughout
uh this last months which is um the
removal of of the need for the Azure
blob storage uh staging step for Azure
SQL and why is that this is actually the
reason why we bring some performance
improvements that that I called out
earlier during the presentation because
we don't need anymore to compress or
decompress the data and store it into
this uh stage and uh the main benefits
here are mainly performance improvements
but also uh this process overall is less
error prone because we reduce the risk
of hitting errors related to the Azure
blob storage
infrastructure great so that was it when
it comes to how is the data replicated
now back to Nicola to show you what the
new UI looks like so to understand how
the new UI is looking like it is
basically split into two parts on the
top you can see the entire status for
your entire replication so you can see
that it is ready to pull additional data
in you can see how many tables were
successful
you can see all of the tables that you
currently have issues there are five
tables that require your
attention and you can also see how many
companies you have replicated and how
many companies are there in total in the
on Prem
database below the overall status you
can see the list of all of the actions
that you did to this environment and
basically this is just a log of steps
that you have done and for all of the
replications that had a problem with
them they are clearly marked as failed
so you can investigate what
happened now if you do a quick mats you
will see that here we have around eight
failed tables and here we are reporting
five tables only so if you're wondering
what is happening so for example if we
drill down here you can see that this
table has failed in this specific
replication however the overall status
is successful and the reason for this is
because there is a later run that can
successfully replicated the the date so
if you ever encounter an issue with data
replication the way to fix it is if you
look into the arrow fix the error and
you simply just invoke another data
replication and then the data is going
to be fixed if you would like to see
what actually happened you can invoke
this show all replication section and
you will see that there is one failed
run and 4 hours later there was a
successful run that successfully copied
the date
so that was all regarding the error riew
if you would like to look at the
companies that were replicated and if
you're looking which companies you're
missing you can easily filter on the
list here and say show me all of the
companies that are not replicated and
now we can show you all of the companies
that you didn't move from on Prem you
can simply select them from here and
then they are going to be created and
you can invoke another
application we are not going to do that
now so we just going to exit without
making any changes you can also look at
the data that was successfully
replicated by using this page here
you're able to filter per company and
one of the things that is very useful to
look at is per database tables because
these tables are sensitive and the risk
is that they can get overwritten and one
of the main tables is the tenant media
table so here it is actually expected to
get a difference because we are going to
always Delta sync the tables that are
per database we are not going to replace
them one of the tables that you cannot
get the information about is the upgrade
tags and the reason for this is because
it is internal and unfortunately it's
not possible to analyze the internal or
obsoleted
tables one of the things that you can
also do is that you can filter on the
table itself so one of the nice
functionality that you can do here is is
that if I would search for the change
log to see what happened with the change
log because I didn't get any data and if
I select the change log entry here the
system is going to tell me that the
change log is not included in the
replication because it is marked with
replicate data false and this is one of
the tables that we got a lot of requests
to include in some of the cases for the
cloud migration so you will be able to
use this new functionality for including
or excluding that we will cover about in
what's
new then the next thing that you can do
is that you can complete the cloud
migration and we also have the options
of posing and abandoning the cloud
migration the only difference between
these two actions is that you are
telling us in which state the tenant is
if you're opposing it means that you
want to continue it if you're abandoning
it it means most likely that you want to
delete the tenant both actions are fully
recoverable so if you regret abandoning
you can simply just configure the cloud
migration again and continue using it
there is not going to be any
consequences of invoking a different AC
okay so that was all about the new UI so
back to you Ricardo regarding the
limitations yes that was very cool so
let's have a closer look into some of
the limitations that currently exist for
the cloud migration so in theory when
you have an environment in SAS we
enforce a strong limit of 300 companies
that is mainly for performance reasons
but we do recommend something like uh
around 250 companies so that you have
room to grow over time if you need to
add more companies when it comes to the
data instead in principle uh we don't
really have a limit so you can
potentially replicate as much data as
you want even exceeding the default
allowed storage capacity that exists in
SAS but be aware however that if you do
so any administ administr operations
that um involve for example creation of
new environments or copying of the
existing environments that basically
affect the storage capacity will be
prevented so you will not be able to
perform these operations and if you do
exceed the quot then when you go live
you are forced to uh purchase additional
storage
capacity great so let's look now into
the next step uh of the data upgrade and
how it works so back to Nicola for this
thanks Ricardo uh so here we are going
to cover the two topics the first topic
is how the upgrade works and the second
is the new functionality that we will
cover in another video and that one is
keeping API upgrade because this one is
taking a long
time so upgr step needs to be invoked as
an absolutely last step in the cloud
migration and the reason why is because
once you invoke the upgrade you will not
be able to do additional replication
or to move additional companies into the
suant and if this happens for you you
will either need to point in time
restore or start over simply delete the
environment and replicate all of the
companies together so the reason why we
introduce this strong rule is because we
are replicating and also upgrading the
per database tables and once we upgrade
the the per database table we simply
cannot allow additional pulls into this
table because we are risking that we are
going to get he upgraded data in the per
database table and we also cannot know
which requests already were upgraded and
which were not thus we are risking many
data Corruptions if we allow running
multiple upgrades and multiple
replications also we have seen that many
partners would pull the data from on
Prem change it in sauce tweak it a
little bit and then they would pull it
from on Prem again and we would strongly
advise not to do this while you are
pulling the data from the on Prem system
do not change the data in SAS database
because you're risking that your changes
are going to be overwritten or you are
also risking that you will confuse the
replication engine so it is not going to
pick up some changes that it should that
it
should our strong recommendation is to
change the data in a single place so
while you're replicating from on Prem do
not change it in sauce if you change it
in SAU do not pull the data from on Prem
again regarding how the upgrade works we
simply invoke the regular upgrade flow
and we ignore the versioning so we are
going to run all of the upgrade code
units this also means that we are going
to put the tenant into the maintenance
mode as you have seen in the demo cut
the access make sure that there is a
single session to prevent any database
locks and to make sure that upgrade is
going to run smoothly we are going to
trigger the upgrade for all of the app
that are installed on the tenant and in
case of the failures we are going to
roll back the data so you can Delta sync
or fix the data and invoke the upgrade
again if you have a custom pte or an
appsource app there is nothing special
that you need to do we will also invoke
your upgrate code as we are invoking
first party upgrate code one of the
things that we strongly recommend is
that once you're done with the
replication is to test the upgrade in a
separate sandbo envir envirment so if
you're replicating to sandbox or to a
production you can copy it to a
different sandbox and then test the
upgrade there of course if you're not
over the data size limits and if you do
it like this then in case the upgrade
runs longer than expected you can still
use the other instance to do the
application to do the additional
replications or invoke a different
upgrade so in the last two versions we
have optimized over 30 long running
upgrade methods so it takes less time to
get to the version 21 or 22 than it took
to get to the version 19 so we are
always recommending to upgrade to the
latest version we are also monitoring
how long the upgrade takes so we are
going to be optimizing long running
upgrade methods once we detect them in
SAU one of the long running upgrade
methods that is usually taking a lot of
time for the large tenants is API
related
upgrade uh for the apis we needed to run
the upgrade because we need to
pre-compute the data so the apis can be
fast and for this reason because we
running it on large tables like
customers items sales invoices it is
usually time consuming for this reason
we have introduced the functionality so
you can run it after the cloud migration
we have a dedicated page that you can
use to invoke the background jobs to
upgrade this data so it's safe to run
after the cloud migration thus we are
recommending to skip this step and we
are going to be talking about it more in
the what's new
session so after you're done with the
upgrade you're ready to complete the
cloud migration and to go live and
before going live we strongly recommend
to do extensive testing in
sandbox then you can complete the cloud
migration there is a functionality that
you can use to setup and map users and
also as the last step you should
configure the Integrations namely API
and data ver sys so setup users uh is
the standard functionality that you can
use from the users list so you can
invoke get users from all 365 there and
configure permissions and and once
you're done with this step you can go to
the cloud migration page and open the
defined user mappings page and here you
have the ability to map the on-prem
users to the SAS users and when you
invoke okay then we are going to go
through all of the tables which are
using username and it is important for
business Logic for example my items
approvals functionality or time sheets
and many other as well and we are going
to go through this data and update the
username so it is going to work in sus
uh one important thing to note here is
that you can do it only once per
environment so you should do it as the
last step because you will not be able
to run it
twice and as a post step you can
configure the database and as a post
step you can configure the data verse
integration again and make sure that the
mappings are correct and run the API
upgrade as I have been talking during
the upgrade
part so one of the frequently asked
questions that we often get is are can
we move additional companies in live
tenants and the answer is we do not
officially support it and we strongly
advise against it because our strong
recommendation to you is to move all of
the companies to S and to go live with
all of the on Prem
companies however we do understand that
in some cases it's not possible or the
customer changes their mind after going
life so it is possible to move
additional companies in life tenants
however you're doing it on your own risk
it is the same as running rapid start or
using any kind of ptes to to fix the
data in case any errors happen you will
need to fix it yourself because we will
not be able to help you to patch the
customer date we will write the
dedicated documentation topic that it
will explain to you how you can do this
safely so make sure that you check out
the documentation in case you need to do
this
all right Ricardo can you show us the
troubleshooting great so of course um
assuming everything goes fine with your
Cloud migration setup and replication
runs you wouldn't need to probably check
any troubleshooting documentation but we
do have a lot of resources available
online that collect actually some of the
most common errors that you may hit
throughout uh process of the process of
cloud migration there's a more generic
page about troubleshooting but also we
do collect some of the most common
issues that can occur either during the
setup or the replication phase so very
useful resources most likely the
solution for the error you're looking
for is already in these
pages and then when it comes to
Telemetry I already said earlier what
are the requirements to enable Telemetry
but assuming you do have Telemetry then
we do collect some of the uh partner
facing Telemetry events on this table uh
just for convenience but they are also
available in this documentation page and
as we can see uh we C we actually
capture pretty much all the important
events that can happen throughout the
cloud migration process uh both when
you're setting up Cloud migration or
starting the replications completing
replications or when any arrows occur so
very useful as well uh to surface
Telemetry um on your
side and a convenient use case uh if you
have Telemetry enabled is of course to
use the powerbi report app available on
app
Source if we drill down uh into this app
specifically we can see that it has a
cloud migration Tab and this one can
become very convenient if you for
example are also running Cloud migration
across different environments and you
want to inspect what is the status of
the migrations throughout the
environment it also provides an
aggregated overview of any errors that
occurred throughout uh Cloud migration
uh for the different environments uh and
some interesting kpis as well and more
interestingly as well without the need
for you to log to the environment and
actually use the web client to inspect
the logs for the cloud migration uh you
can also inspect them from here directly
in the powerbi app so that's also very
convenient and
useful last but not least it's also
interesting that you can set up alerts
and email notifications uh based on such
dmetry events again these are some of
the most common Cloud migration events
but they are fully documented in the
pages that we have linked uh and not
only you can receive email notifications
but also for example set up teams uh to
receive such notifications very very
simple and straightforward uh again
fully documented in our
documentation all right so that was all
for today and before we end the
presentation we would like to ask you to
try out the cloud migration there is no
need to wait you can just take a
database and test the cloud migration to
a Sandbox we are often getting questions
from the partners how much space is the
database going to take or how much time
is it going to take to replicate and
upgrade the database you can simply just
take the database and try it out to a
Sandbox and see for yourself because
it's going to take less space And
depending on the data structure it
depends how long time is it going to
take to replicate an
upgrade so of course don't forget to set
up the Telemetry as we've seen it is
also a very useful uh source of
information that can help you
troubleshoot issues along the way and of
course always rely on the documentation
that's probably the most useful resource
that you have available online yes and
we will be updating it on the timely
basis and as the last step you can join
us on ymer where you can ask us
additional questions or provide feedback
so we will be there to support you thank
you very much for your attention thank
you